White House Tapes: Conversation 948-012, July 11, 1973
National Archives and Records Administration
Society of American Archivists
White House Tapes: Conversation 948-012
July 11, 1973
Nixon, Richard M. (President); Connally, John B.; Woods, Rose Mary; Sanchez, Manolo
597542 White House Tapes 17409633 Oval Office Sound Recordings 7450151 Audiotape 948
Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum
948-012
On July 11, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, John B. Connally, Rose Mary Woods, and Manolo Sanchez met in the Oval Office of the White House from 3:03 pm to 4:22 pm. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 948-012 of the White House Tapes. Topics of conversation included United States and global economies; the Nixon Administration's economic policies and actions, specifically Phase III of the Economic Stabilization Program under the Economic Stabilization Act of 1970; export controls, price controls, world food supplies and food prices; agriculture, dairy products, farm program, and Congressional legislation; Watergate, the investigation by the Senate Select Committe on Presidential Campaign Activitiees (also known as the Ervin Committee), hearing witnesses and testimony, a focus on the Internal Revenue Service (IRS), press coverage regarding President Nixon's San Clemente property, and campaign contributions; Connally's domestic and foreign travel, especially to the Soviet Union; and President Nixon's schedule.
This Oval Office recording is part of the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes, a secret taping program authorized by President Richard Nixon and active from 1971 to 1973.
July 11, 1973
July 11, 1973
certain
3:03 pm
4:22 pm
certain
Recording Location and Taping System History
Beginning in 1971, President Richard Nixon authorized the installation of a secret taping system in selected portions of the White House, Cabinet Room, Oval Office, Old Executive Office Building, and Camp David. Collectively, these recordings constitute the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes.
In February 1971, the United State Secret Service installed listening devices in the White House. They placed seven microphones in the Oval Office: five in the President's desk and one on each side of the fireplace. The Secret Service technicians wired these devices to central mixers that were then connected to recorders in an old locker room in the White House basement. These recordings became known as the Oval Office recordings.
This system was a secret taping system maintained by the Secret Service. Only President Nixon, H. R. Haldeman, and a few of the President's close personal assistants knew the system existed. One of its key features was that the recording equipment in the Oval Office, the EOB office, at Camp David, and on the telephones was sound-activated, operating without a conscious decision by the President to record a specific conversation. The taping system was tied to the Presidential Locator System, which was also operated by the Secret Service, and was designed to continue recording for fifteen to thirty seconds after the President left the room.
On July 16, 1973, Special Assistant to the President Alexander Butterfield revealed the existence of the White House taping system during his testimony before the Senate Watergate Committee. Following this public revelation, White House Chief of Staff Alexander Haig ordered the removal of the entire presidential taping system.
Collection Overview
Conversation Summary
On July 11, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, John B. Connally, Rose Mary Woods, and Manolo Sanchez met in the Oval Office of the White House from 3:03 pm to 4:22 pm. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 948-012 of the White House Tapes.
Topics of conversation included United States and global economies; the Nixon Administration's economic policies and actions, specifically Phase III of the Economic Stabilization Program under the Economic Stabilization Act of 1970; export controls, price controls, world food supplies and food prices; agriculture, dairy products, farm program, and Congressional legislation; Watergate, the investigation by the Senate Select Committe on Presidential Campaign Activitiees (also known as the Ervin Committee), hearing witnesses and testimony, a focus on the Internal Revenue Service (IRS), press coverage regarding President Nixon's San Clemente property, and campaign contributions; Connally's domestic and foreign travel, especially to the Soviet Union; and President Nixon's schedule.
Audio Quality
The audio quality of the Nixon White House Tapes is generally poor. While some locations generated better quality recordings than others, inferior recording equipment, cheap tape stock, improper microphone placement, taping system malfunctions, volume fluctuation, background noise, and electrical interference contributed to the poor quality of the recordings. Other noises greatly affect the audibility of conversations, including such small happenings as the signing of documents or the clinking of coffee cups.
As a result of the microphone coverage, Oval Office conversations have clear audio relative to other Nixon White House Tapes. Even still, extraneous room noises and background sounds are evident and can obscure portions of conversations. The microphones in the desk picked up the sound of anyone writing on the desk or the setting down a coffee cup or a glass. Furthermore, the desk microphones captured the sound of President Nixon's chair banging into the desk, the President's feet banging on the desk as he put his feet up, and the sound of the President's knees knocking against the kneewell of his desk. The microphone installed near the telephone captured the ringing of the telephone, which sometimes blocked out small portions of conversation. On occasion, the helicopter rotor blades from Marine One completely obliterated conversation taking place in the Oval Office. The recording system also captured the sirens of ambulances, fire engines, and police vehicles as they blared in through open windows. On occasion, the opening and closing of interior and exterior doors briefly interfered with conversations.
Nature of the Recording
The White House Tapes comprise secretly recorded human conversation. Most participants were unaware that their meetings and telephone calls were being recorded. The taping system captured often unstructured and free-flowing discussions between close personal associates intimately familiar with the topic. As a result, users may find the recorded conversations difficult to follow.
Collection Arrangement
About the Subject Log
To assist listeners in understanding the conversation and finding segments pertinent to their own interests, a team of archivists has created a Subject Log, which outlines major topics, names, and organizations in sequential order.
Logs include action statements, which indicate when someone entered or exited a room. Action statements are underlined.
If a conversation recorded in one of the offices also captures a telephone conversation, a cross-reference to the corresponding telephone recording is provided.
If a telephone recording also captures a conversation taking place in one of the offices, a cross-reference to the corresponding room conversation is provided.
Logs indicate which portions, if any, were reviewed under the 2007 Deed of Gift.
In some cases, the Watergate Special Prosecution Force or court-ordered mandates resulted in a transcript of the entire conversation or portions of conversation. For these portions, archivists have provided a citation to the related transcript.
Audio Format
This conversation was recorded to audiotape on a system maintained by the United States Secret Service. The National Archives transferred the original audiotape to Digital Audio Tape (DAT), which, in turn, was later converted to digital audio files.
The audio recording of this conversation has been digitized and made available to the public.
The White House Tapes are currently undergoing preservation remastering, from which digital derivatives will be made and released to the public as appopriate.
Determination Categories
These processing categories are governed by the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA); and the 2007 Deed of Gift. These categories are based upon the constitutional and statutory duties of the President of the United States, as well as the Watergate investigation.
Location of Recording
Oval Office, White House, Washington, D.C.
Related Topics
United States. President (1969-1974: Nixon); Audiotapes; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Presidents -- United States
Topics of Conversation
People
Connally, John B.; Nixon, Richard M. (President); Sanchez, Manolo; Woods, Rose Mary
Places and Governments
Soviet Union; San Clemente (Calif.)
Organizations
Economic Stabilization Program (U.S.); United States. Congress; United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities; United States. Internal Revenue Service
Topics
Agriculture; Campaign funds; Economic conditions; Economic policy; Economic stabilization; Food supply; Legislation; Presidential schedules; Wage-price policy
Digitized Audio
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as an MP3 file.
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as a Broadcast WAVE Format (BWF) file.
Conversation Subject Log
- The President met with John B. Connally.
  - Cabinet meeting, July 11, 1973
  - National economy
    - Export controls
      - Exceptions
        - Meat
      - Ceiling on prices
      - Compared to previous action
    - President's program
      - Need for taper
      - Short-term compared to long-term objectives
      - Government's role
        - Consumer expectations
          - Food prices
    - Fruits and vegetables
      - Seasonal fluctuations
    - Meat
      - Ceiling on price
        - Earl L. Butz's view
      - Beef compared with pork
        - Hog prices
- Rose Mary Woods entered at 3:08 pm.
  - President's schedule
    - Forthcoming meeting with Senators
      - Message
      - Julie Nixon Eisenhower
- Woods left at 3:10 pm.
  - National economy
    - Meat
      - Hog prices
        - Fluctuations
          - Cycles, overproduction
      - Ceiling on price
    - President's program
      - Previous meeting
        - Support
        - President's strategy
      - Arthur F. Burns's views
      - Controls
        - Duration
        - Exemptions
        - Graduated approach
          - Public confidence
        - Inflation
        - Phase-out timetable
        - Food
          - 60-day
            - Input
      - Livestock
      - Beef-raising cycle
        - Butz's view
        - Hog production
          - Feed prices
            - Corn, grain
            - Profitability
              - Margin
          - Single supplier
            - Flexibility
      - Agriculture
        - Butz's views
        - Leslie C. Arends's views
        - Controls
          - Farms, businessmen, labor leaders
            - Compared with consumers
          - Consumers' support
          - Duration
      - Butz
      - Poultry production
        - Price of eggs
        - Cyclic production
          - Purina
            - Market dominance
          - Poultry compared to hog production
            - Broilers
          - Purina
            - Feed subsidies
        - Supply of broilers
    - Pork packing houses
      - Closings
        - Sanitary laws
    - Cattle compared to chickens
      - Grain
    - Export controls
      - Connally's support
- Manolo Sanchez entered at an unknown time after 3:10 pm.
  - Refreshments
- Sanchez left at an unknown time before 4:22 pm.
  - National economy
    - Export controls
      - Duration
      - Possible effects
        - Priorities
          - Domestic consumption compared to world consumption
      - Timing
        - Crop yields
        - Agricultural acreage
    - World food supplies
      - Prosperity
      - Soviet Union
        - Leonid I. Brezhnev's decisions
          - Consumer
      - People's Republic of China [PRC]
        - Transition of economy
          - Future strain of PRC demand
          - Payment
            - Balance of trade
              - Textiles
      - World food shortage
        - US role
        - Latin America's role
        - Brazil
        - Latin America's role
          - Agricultural acreage
            - Compared to Midwest, Texas
            - Development of roads, refrigeration
        - South America
          - Population
            - Poverty
            - Birth control
          - Studies
            - Efficiency of land use
        - US expertise
          - Soviet Union
    - Price controls
      - Industry
      - John T. Dunlop's views
    - Phase III
      - Difficulties
        - Timing
    - Controls
      - Goal
        - Removal of controls
      - President's possible statements to farmers
        - Pittsburgh, Des Moines, Illinois
      - President's possible statement to livestock industry
      - Food prices
        - Popular views
          - Balance of payments
          - Japan, PRC, Soviet Union
          - Strength of dollar
    - US position in global economy
      - Strength of dollar
        - Paris, Zurich, Geneva, Bonn
      - Soviet Union grain deal
        - Terms
    - Agricultural prosperity
      - Regions of US
        - South, Midwest, West
        - Southeast
          - Peanuts, soybeans, cotton, corn, cattle
        - Southwest, Texas, Oklahoma, Louisiana
          - Soybeans, wheat
          - Wheat
        - Midwest
        - West
          - California
        - Economic and political importance
      - Cattle prices
        - Connally's sale of heifers, July 10, 1973
          - Feed
          - Beef production
    - Agriculture
      - Prices
        - Corn
          - Yield
          - Net profit
        - Wheat
      - Butz's view
        - 60-day
      - Export controls
        - Duration
          - Crop cycle
      - Corn production
        - Compared with previous years, estimates
        - Dunlop's view
          - Need for controls
          - Council of Economic Advisors [CEA]
        - Export controls
        - Predictions
          - Impact of weather, insects, storms
        - Frederick B. Dent's, others' statement
          - Export controls
        - Crop year
    - Labor
      - Forthcoming negotiations
        - Jobs
        - Real income
        - Possibility of strikes
      - Increase in real disposable income
        - Compared to inflation
    - Food prices
      - Consumption of meat
        - President's childhood diet
        - Increase in production, consumption
          - Per capita
    - Farm program
      - Farm legislation
        - Subsidies
        - Anachronism
        - Signing of legislation
        - Public statements
      - Previous surpluses
      - Free market
      - Fears
      - Parity
        - 1968 campaign
          - Hubert H. Humphrey
      - Grain program
        - Connally's farm
          - Soil Conservation Service
            - [Higara ?]
              - Chicken feed
              - Implications of rules
            - Deferred grain program
              - Implications of rules
                - Export controls
            - Maize
              - Cattle feed, hay, chicken feed, hog feed
            - Cross-purposes
            - Deferred grain program
              - Agriculture Department
      - Farm bill
        - Parity for milk
          - Milk producers
            - Dairy co-operatives [co-ops]
      - Milk
        - Previous supplies
        - Current production
        - Competition from overseas
          - Europe
            - Cheese, butter
        - Dairy co-ops
          - Compared with unions
          - Demand
        - Price supports
      - Pending legislation
        - President's approval
        - Senate
          - Carl T. Curtis
          - Milton R. Young
        - Senate bill compared to House of Representatives bill
          - Curtis
        - William R. Poage's conversation with President
          - Leonid I. Brezhnev signing ceremony
        - President's possible veto
          - Connally's view
            - Support prices
          - Goal
          - Approval
            - Appeal to East Coasters
          - Sellers' market
          - Possible effects of veto
            - President's credibility
              - Labor-Management Advisory Committee
    - Role of government
      - Problem solving
      - Private initiative
        - Businessmen, farmers, consumers
      - Compared to Europe
        - Great Britain, France
        - Germany
          - Labor relations
      - Japan
        - Labor rates
      - Europe, Germany, Japan, USSR, PRC
      - Private initiative
        - "Pioneer spirit"
        - US deficit
        - Midwest, South
          - Compared to East
            - Eastern establishment
    - President's leadership
      - Watergate
        - Distraction
        - Timing
          - Forthcoming testimony of H. R. ("Bob") Haldeman, and John D. Ehrlichman
            - Possible outcome
  - Watergate
    - Ervin Committee hearings
      - Forthcoming testimony of Haldeman and Ehrlichman
    - Henry A. Kissinger's conversation with President
      - Thomas W. Braden
        - Nelson A. Rockefeller
      - Braden, Frank F. Mankiewicz, and George S. McGovern
        - Plan
          - John W. Dean, III
          - Duration, scope of investigation
            - Public interest
    - Public opinion
    - Ervin Committee hearings
      - Witness list
        - Haldeman, Ehrlichman, John N. Mitchell, and Herbert W. Kalmbach
    - Internal Revenue Service [IRS]
      - Enemies list
        - President's and Connally's knowledge
        - Dr. Michael DeBakey
        - Investigations
      - Audits of President's returns in 1961 and 1962
        - Robert F. ("Bobby") Kennedy
        - Leaks of income tax returns
      - Dean's list
        - Request for investigations
          - Johnnie M. Walters's response
      - Investigation of Connally while Secretary of Treasury
      - Investigations
        - Charles G. ("Bebe") Rebozo
        - William F. ("Billy") Graham
        - Dr. W. Kenneth Riland
        - Walters's response
      - Robert H. Abplanalp
      - Stories regarding President's San Clemente property
        - Campaign funds
        - President's response regarding finances
        - President's finances
          - Abplanalp
          - Rebozo
          - Los Angeles Times story regarding Teamsters
  - Deed of Gift Segment
    Restricted per 2007 Deed of Gift
    - [Withdrawn Item No. 5], withdrawal-948-012-w005; 00:00:43 (Timecode ##:##:## - ##:##:##)
      Restricted as Personal-Returnable Material
  - Watergate
    - Stories regarding President's San Clemente property
      - General Services Administration [GSA] improvements
        - United States Secret Service [USSS]
        - Freedom of Information Act [FOIA] request
          - Press coverage, public reaction
        - Thomas J. ("Tom") Steed's statement
          - Approval
          - Justification
            - John F. Kennedy's assassination
            - Robert F. ("Bobby") Kennedy's assassination [?]
        - USSS
          - Fence
          - Railroad tracks
            - Mexican-Americans
      - President's possible response
        - Facilities at Lyndon B. Johnson's ranch
          - Airstrip
          - Public knowledge
        - Facilities at Dwight D. Eisenhower's ranch
        - Hyannis Port, Massachusetts
        - USSS orders
          - Contrasted with President's preferences
        - Net worth
    - White House response
      - President's possible statement
        - Timing
        - Content
          - Watergate compared to President's San Clemente property
    - Abplanalp
      - Precision Valve Co.
        - Anti-trust suit
          - Jewish plaintiffs
          - Justice Department
          - Bertram L. Podell's statement
      - Abplanalp, Rebozo
        - Reluctance to use Presidential plane
    - Robert L. Vesco
    - White House response
      - President's possible statements
        - Aplanalp, Rebozo
          - Connally's viewpoint
        - Need to build sympathy
          - Abplanalp
          - Rebozo
    - Rebozo
      - Howard Hughes's contribution
        - Maurice Stans
        - Handling
          - Return
          - Kalmbach
          - Federal Bureau of Investigation [FBI] agent [First name unknown] Calhoun
            - Amount
    - 1972 campaign contributions
      - Stans
        - Compared to McGovern's campaign
        - Source of funding
      - White House response
        - Possible public statements
      - Possible Congressional action
        - Possible effects
      - Return to contributors
      - Contributors
        - Business people
        - Possible statements
        - Ervin Committee investigation in Houston, Texas
          - Handling by Connally
          - George Brown
            - Statement
    - Archibald Cox
      - Forthcoming White House response
      - Duties
  - Connally's schedule
    - Foreign travel
      - Brezhnev
        - Timing of trip
          - August 3
        - Business interests
          - Possible task force
        - Connally's conversation with Walter B. Wriston and William E. Simon
      - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics [USSR]
      - Romania, Poland, Czechoslovakia
      - Middle East
        - Advisability
      - USSR
      - PRC
        - Connally's personal interests
      - USSR compared with PRC
        - Order, timing of trips
        - President's role
      - PRC and Japan
        - Timing
      - Connally's availability
      - PRC
        - President's experience
  - President's schedule
    - Public appearances after Labor Day
      - Compared to campaign
        - Response to opponents
  - Connally's schedule
    - Domestic travel, speaking appearances
      - Florida
        - Edward J. Gurney
      - Kansas
        - Robert J. Dole
        - Kansas Republican Committee
      - Oklahoma, Arizona, California, Oregon, Illinois
      - Ohio
      - New York
      - Ohio, Pennsylvania
        - Frank Dale in Cincinnati
        - [Horace] Chapman ("Chappie") Rose in Cleveland
        - Preston Wolfe in Columbus
    - Trip to USSR
      - Timing
      - Eastern Europe
        - Poland
      - Announcement
        - Ronald L. Ziegler and Alexander M. Haig, Jr.
        - Trip preparations, rejoining law firm
        - Timing, focus
          - President's forthcoming speech
  - Jamaica
    - Statehood
  - Nassau [Bahamas]
    - Independence
      - Likelihood of success
    - Government
      - US action
    - Population
    - Poverty
    - Military, diplomatic corps
      - United Nations [UN] ambassador, ambassador to US
      - Appropriations
    - Tourism
      - Taxation
        - Hotels
    - Abplanalp
      - Residence
  - Watergate
    - White House
      - Timing
      - Effect
    - Popular view
    - Ervin Committee hearings
      - Mitchell, Haldeman, Ehrlichman
        - Televised testimony
    - Popular view
      - Saturation
  - John A. Love
    - Appointment to Energy Policy Office
      - Need for encouragement
    - Meeting with [Shah of Iran] Mohammed Reza Pahlavi
      - Connally's attendance
  - Connally's schedule
    - Forthcoming dinner
- Connally left at 4:22 pm.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Portions of this conversation are closed to the public:
One (1) withdrawal as Personal-Returnable